<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The key of David that openeth the gates to the citie of God also, of faith and repentance, and how they are wrought, and brought to passe, and whether faith be commanded in the law or not.</title>
            <author>T. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21520.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4869</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23981771</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23981771</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27055</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27055)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1840:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The key of David that openeth the gates to the citie of God also, of faith and repentance, and how they are wrought, and brought to passe, and whether faith be commanded in the law or not.</title>
                  <author>T. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Haueland for Nathaniel Fosbrooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: T.S.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-F⁸ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27055:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27055:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE KEY OF DAVID, That openeth the Gates to the Citie of GOD: <hi>Alſo,</hi> Of Faith and Repentance, and how they are wrought, and brought to paſſe: and whether Faith be commanded in the Law, or not.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Thomas Haueland</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Fosbrooke.</hi> 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27055:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27055:2"/>
            <head>TO HIM THAT LABORETH, AND is heauy laden; thirſteth, and would haue reſt; Grace, mercie, <hi>and peace from God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and from Chriſt our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, be multiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inding of late (in a little Treatiſe) a great treaſure, I thought moſt fit to preſent it, to him that would beſt eſteeme of it. If then thou be a good Lapidiſt, and canſt iudge or diſcerne of a perfect ſtone; heerin thou haſt that Pearle of price, for which the Ieweller ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentureth,
<pb facs="tcp:27055:3"/>by ſea, by land, by fire, by water to attaine.</p>
            <p>A wiſe builder will be ſure to lay a good foundation: a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Souldiour will not be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed in the daie of battell: neither will a diſcreet Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner careleſſely reſpect, how to auoide the perils of a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous gulfe.</p>
            <p>How much more (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) behooueth it thee, wiſely to forecaſt how to turne ouer the leaues of thy life, that thy paſſage be not ſtopt, in the way of thy pilgrimage, and thou diſappointed of the land of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which pertaineth to ſuch onely as gratiouſlie and in due
<pb facs="tcp:27055:3"/>time doe begin, and conſtantlie continue vnto the end?</p>
            <p>Be not then like to the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Babel,</hi> that bring mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ſtones, and ſtones for clay: but as the wiſe virgins, did prouidently prouide that their Lampes might bee readie againſt the comming of the Bridegroome: ſo thou likewiſe, ſee that thy foundation be ſure, and thy building raiſed vp, not with ſtubble and ſtraw, which will rot and periſh, but with lime and ſtone that is firme and ſtrong, which (though the raine doe beate, and the winds blow,) yet beeing ſtrongly built vpon the Rocke, it ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:27055:4"/>ſtand faſt for euer.</p>
            <p>If thus thou intend wiſely to erect a Tower, turne ouer the leafe, conſider this plot, wherein is the frame of a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous building, not made with mens hands, or ſuch a one as periſheth, but framed by God in a wonderful manner. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou ſhalt ſee how the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is laid, and the Roofe couered: what manner of men they be for whom the holie Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is prepared, &amp; vnto whom the glorie thereof is denied: how the way is made plaine vnto it: and by what meanes wee muſt enter thereinto. Let it not bee lightly regarded of
<pb facs="tcp:27055:4"/>thee, ſeeing it is now high time thy worke were begun: Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is at hand; the windes doe begin to blow: If thou want harbour, the ſtormy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts will periſh thee. Thus leauing thee to thy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and praying for thy good ſpeed, I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine, leaſt worthy,</hi> T. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27055:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27055:5"/>
            <head>THE KEY OF DAVID, that openeth the Gates to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of GOD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE generall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankinde, being already brought vnto ſuch wretched paſſe, and forlorne miſerie, partly by naturall corruption, partly by leaud con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, that nothing is more euident and certaine, then the faſt comming on, and drawing neare of that appointed day, in vvhich muſt bee rendered vnto euery one the deſerued puniſhment of all their falſe opinions, and vvicked deeds: who would not in this caſe, iudge it his part and duetie, greatly to eſteeme, and worthily to receiue with attentiue eares, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27055:6"/>counſell and inſtruction vvhich teacheth the way, how the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined vengeance of that approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doomes day may bee eſcaped. To performe this, is an hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter indeed: yet a very worthy work: In the ſetting forth whereof, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the more extraordinary pains to bee required, becauſe nothing hath been more aſſayed, by ſome aduenturous diuines of this age, yet nothing leſſe brought to a point and finiſhed.</p>
            <p>As for this my labour, ſuch as it is, I bequeath it to poſteritie; for I neither ſeeke after nor reckon of, ſuch common Patrons, as theſe daies affoord: Becauſe I haue hated euen with perfect deteſtation, the nice vntowardneſſe of theſe daintie times, running after each palpable error of former ages, with ſtrong emulation; but denying to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, with enuious folly, all bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of things preſent, be they neuer ſo good: And being daily and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually aduertiſed, by the plaine
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27055:6"/>and ſenſible proofe of ſo many miſchiefes, comming in troupes vpon them, yet neuertheleſſe (a iuſt plague for fooles) they ſtil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſottiſh, and without vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Therefore I appeale vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the age next following: not this now conſiſting of fleſhly minded and worldly men, that will bee ſet to ſale, and corrupted: but that ſucceeding after this, which ſhalbe filled with the ſpirit, and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: This ſmall treatiſe, doe I betake vnto that age: whereof ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I haue no feare, leſt it ſhould giue partiall ſentence, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled with fauour, or impoiſoned with malice, I am come to this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hope, to thinke that it vvill entertaine this worke, with all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe: And (if truth deceiue mee not) will preſerue and keepe it ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from time to time. But before I come to the point it ſelfe, I think it not amiſſe, briefely to repeate the flouriſh and preamble of B. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture; wherein both the ſeate of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27055:7"/>the queſtion now in hand, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined. And whereof betwixt him and mee, there is full agreement without any controuerſie: Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Apoſtle, whilſt hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth the Romans of the way, and meanes to attaine ſaluation; hee teacheth them, that the ſame doth wholly conſiſt in nothing elſe, but the Goſpell onely. And the Goſpell is the free exhibiting, or gratious vouchſafing of Gods fauour, <hi>viz.</hi> The mercie and loue of God for Chriſts ſake, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſometimes calleth the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God, ſometimes the power of GOD vnto ſaluation. And he ſaith that it is reuealed, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted and communicated to men by the meanes of faith, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Abac.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>The Iuſt ſhall liue by faith.</hi> And leſt any man aduancing himſelfe in the fleſhly conceiued worthines of his own perfections, ſhould bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwade himſelfe, that by ſome helpe or other, either of naturall ſtrength, inclination, or elſe of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27055:7"/>learning, skill, and profound know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or of ceremonious worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and cuſtomary deuotions, hee might procure this Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and ſaluation; this is the very firſt thing, which the Apoſtle ſetteth in the fore-front of his diſputation: handling the ſame (as you may ſee) from the 18. ver. of the firſt chapter to the 28. ver. of the 3. where hee maketh a diſtribution, or diuiſion of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, into two ſorts or companies: The former wherof, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all the Gentils, the latter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth the Jewes onely. And firſt of all, hee pulleth downe the arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie of the Gentils; becauſe how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer that which may be knowne of GOD, bee written in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Tables of their hearts: yet they not regarding this diuine and naturall illumination, did run head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vpon all wickedneſſe, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of God, <hi>luſt, couetouſnes, enuy, ſpite, cruelty, ſtrife, &amp;c.</hi> And that they might fully reach vnto the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27055:8"/>higheſt outrage of rebellion, and filthy behauiour: Hee layeth to their charge, that they are guilty of ſtrange &amp; execrable vncleanneſſe: hauing indeede moſt foulely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſuch loathſome abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, againſt nature it ſelfe, as are not to be named.</p>
            <p>After he hath thus brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the haughtineſſe of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils; he then ſetteth vpon the Iewes alſo: whom with two encounters, hee vtterly ouerthroweth: Firſt, becauſe they had wickedly falſified with their corrupt interpretations, and had tranſgreſſed or broken that Lawe of God, which in expreſſe wordes was deliuered to them by the hand of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Secondly, hee confoundeth them plainely, by alleadging the teſtimonie of the <hi>Prophet,</hi> who being ordained a <hi>King</hi> and a <hi>Prophet,</hi> to them which were vnder the lawe, thus he writeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, in a certaine place of the Pſal. <hi>There is not a good one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.53.</note> 
               <hi>ſurely not one: There is not that doth good,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27055:8"/>not ſo much as one.</hi> Thus at the laſt all workes of mortall men, vvhich they made (as it were,) their props and ſtaies to reſt themſelues vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, beeing quite caſt away, hee draweth to an end in this manner: <hi>Therefore wee conclude that a man is iuſtified by faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28.</note> 
               <hi>without the works of the Lawe, (viz.)</hi> without any workes or deeds of our owne: whether they beframed according to the lawe of God, written in the fleſhly tables of our hearts, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected after the will of GOD, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen once in ſtone, or faſhioned by any other writing and rule of diuine ordinances.</p>
            <p>When as therefore B. did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that all ſaluation and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of mankinde, was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced wholly in the alone grace of Ieſus Chriſt: (Viz.) in the free fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God, inſomuch as hee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth pitie vpon them, and loueth them in Chriſt Ieſus: And that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo God ſetteth forth vnto man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde one onely way, one onelie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27055:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>meanes, which indeede is faith, by which as by a certaine ladder, they muſt get vp to the attainement of this grace. When hee ſaw that theſe things were ſo, the man was preſently inflamed, with a paſſing earneſt zeale, thorowly to informe his hearers, concerning this ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and wonderfull benefit, or gift of faith: and for that end, took vpon him to vnfold this verſe or ſentence of the Apoſtle (Viz.) <hi>We conclude, that a man is iuſtified by faith, &amp;c.</hi> In explication where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hee promiſeth that he will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue two things: Firſt, what this ſo precious and excellent faith is, by which the righteouſnes of God is ſaid hold vpon or apprehended: Secondly, touching the workes of the lawe, and amongſt all other points thereof, that which is the chiefeſt of the reſt, whether faith is to bee reckoned amongſt thoſe things, which are commanded in the lawe. This large vnder-taker of ſo great a charge, will we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27055:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the very ſame way that hee is gone. And firſt wee will conſider what faith it ſelfe is, what bee the cauſes, and parts thereof, and after what manner it is wrought, and bred in men: In the next place, we will diſcuſſe that point, whether it bee commanded in the lawe or not.</p>
            <p>But if a definition of faith bee required, ſaith B. I ſuppoſe that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to bee preferred before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which the Apoſtle deliuereth, writing to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> when he ſaith, that <hi>faith is the ground of things hoped for, and the euidence of things which are not ſeene.</hi> In which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion (to ſpeake nothing of the reſt) I finde fault with <hi>B.</hi> for two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt and chiefely, becauſe this word faith, beeing of many ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and carying diuers ſenſes or meanings in holy ſcripture; hee did not afore all other things diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh that kinde or nature of faith, which hee would define vnto his hearers from all the reſt, by which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27055:10"/>meanes ſurely, that faith whereof our queſtion is: (beeing ſet apart by it ſelfe, and freed from all incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience of commixture, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters) would then bee kept in our open ſight, plaine, ſingle, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confuſed, and alwaies like it ſelfe. How much better is the aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Tertul. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Marcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> of one that giueth much good aduiſe? when it is ſo, ſaith he: The difficultie ariſeth, as well from the ambiguitie, and doubtfulneſſe of meaning, as from the obſcuritie or hiddennes of matter: Then there muſt be firſt a diſtinction, after that a definition; for as the ſame writer ſaith very well: The faithfull inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, or true meaning of words and names of things, doth affoord a ſafe and ſute way rightly to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, what bee their due proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reproofe, which I caſt vpon <hi>B.</hi> is, becauſe hee hath affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the Apoſtolique writer, doth in this place, giue a definition of faith: as if belike the man were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27055:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>ignorant, that it is a farre other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to make a deſcription of a thing, or to extoll it, with ſome high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, then it is to expreſſe the ſame by a definition: For euery definition, is a ſhort and limited de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of that thing, which thou wouldeſt define, from the neareſt and moſt proper cauſes therof: For if any ſhall ſay, that a man is moſt excellent of creatures, that hee is a breefe or mappe of the whole vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall world, and that for the ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, or faſhioning of him, the moſt mighty and bleſſed GOD, did fould vp (as it were) in one lumpe, a certaine repreſentation, and nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſemblance of all things, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer are either by our ſight diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or elſe be farre aboue our view and paſt our knowing; hee that ſhould thus ſpeake, might elegant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indeed, and wiſely deſcribe a man: neuertheleſſe, all this yeelds vs not the definition of a man, nor ſheweth properly what he is.</p>
            <p>And after the ſelfe-ſame manner,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27055:11"/>euen here our Apoſtlelike writer; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch, as he was to deale with a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that euer was enemy to true godlineſſe, which at all times refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the righteouſneſſe appointed by GOD, euen the faith of Ieſus Chriſt; hee doth ſo much the more aduance, or ſet forth at large, the dignitie and worth of faith; telling them, that therein conſiſteth full and wholly, both the promiſe and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, and what benefit ſoeuer, a godly and bleſſed life requireth, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither with all the ſubſtance of things eternall, which by hope are to bee expected: Neither could their fathers, ſaith he, haue euer plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, by any other good parts or vertues of their owne; but by this faith onely.</p>
            <p>In which diſcourſe, verily hee makes a well garniſhed deſcription of faith: ſetting it out with honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble words, of great commendations, well beſeeming the excellency ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; yet doth hee not define it: for if hee had done that, then thou muſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27055:11"/>needs bee a man, very ill aduiſed, to goe and ſeeke another definition thereof, as thou haſt done. But now at length, let vs come to the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith: which wee haue taken in hand, and before I doe define the nature thereof, what it is (leſt I ſhould fall into <hi>B.</hi> errour) I will plainely ſhew the diuers ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it. This word <hi>faith</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, how it is taken in humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I will not buſie my ſelf at this time to declare: But in holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, it hath reference, ſometimes vnto God, ſometimes vnto men; if to God, then it importeth nothing elſe, but the ſtedfaſt and vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able truth of his decree and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; if vnto men, then it ſignifieth, either the doctrine of the Goſpell it ſelfe, or the faithfull diſcharge of their office that preach the ſame, or elſe ſome ſpeciall gift, which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt vouchſafeth vnto vs: Now of thoſe gifts of the holy ghoſt, there are but three onely, which are inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, by the name of faith: For ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27055:12"/>the knowledge of that great myſterie, which the holy ghoſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealeth, and the certaine vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the truth of GOD, is called faith, which may fitly be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, either hiſtoricall Faith, or the faith of knowledge.</p>
            <p>Now for this <hi>Faith,</hi> although al the Saints haue it in ſome meaſure, yet is it not peculiar to them alone, for vſually many wicked and filthy, doe excell in this: yea, euen Satan him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, doth goe farre beyond all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in this kind of <hi>Faith.</hi> For hee beleeueth that God is the creatour of the world, that hee is Lord ouer all, and acknowledgeth himſelfe vnder his dominion: And that God made all things by his word; as it is written,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.9.</note> 
               <hi>He ſpake the word, and they were made;</hi> he beleeueth this word, to be that which is both called the Son of God, and is ſo indeed: by whom and for whom all things were made, begotten before all time, the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and wiſe God, alwaies bleſſed for euer and euer: Who after diuers
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27055:12"/>maners appeared to the fathers, and ſpake by the Prophets: Hee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that the ſame Word in fulneſſe of time, came downe into the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, by the power of the holy ghoſt, was made fleſh, and of her was born that annointed Sauiour, thence-forth called Ieſus Chriſt: that the ſame wrought great miracles, preached that hidden myſtery of the will of GOD, which beeing at that time almoſt buried in obliuion, was long before foretold by the Prophets, and hee likewiſe ſealed, and confirmed it by his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Hee beleeueth furthermore, that the ſame Word, or ſonne of GOD Chriſt Ieſus, after all this, was nailed to the croſſe, dead and buried ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, the third day roſe to life againe, and was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp into heauen, &amp; ſitteth there at the right hand of the Father, which hath <hi>put all things vnder bis feete:</hi> Becauſe hee alone is worthy. Hee is alſo moſt vndoubtedly perſwaded, that the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, did for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27055:13"/>ſupplying his own place, ſend down from heau en the powerfull efficacie of his holy ſpirit, to guide and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne his Church: which paſt que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is nothing elſe, but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and ſocietie of his holy ones, in all places, here and there ſcattered ouer the whole world: And hee beleeueth, that this companie of Gods owne people, is ſanctified by the <hi>lauer of repentance, and the word of faith;</hi> to bee an holy nation for euer, to the Lord himſelfe. Hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth moreouer, that the ſame Lord Ieſus, ſhall at the laſt day come in the clouds, with greateſt power, and ſhall then take vp the Saints to receiue reward of eternall life, and to enioy the promiſes of heauen.</p>
            <p>But as for the vngodly and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, his comming ſhall bee to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them, vnto euerlaſting fire: yet both ſorts ſhall in that day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their fleſhly bodies, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration whereof, they ſhall from the firſt death returne againe. And with thus much faith, the very skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migers
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27055:13"/>of Satan: <hi>Bribers, promoters, hypocrites, witches, heretickes, repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, couetous perſons, whoremongers and filthy fellows,</hi> of which kinde of beleeuers, at this day the whole world is full, betwixt whom and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels this is all the difference: the one by not beleeuing, like wretches as they are, doe come vnto perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the other by beleeuing in ſuch wofull manner, as they doe, bring themſelues to moſt damnable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: This kinde of faith, if any one would define, he may well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his minde, in ſaying that it is nothing elſe but a ſure knowledge and a ſetled aſſent of the minde, by which any man moſt vndoubtedly beleeueth ſuch things, to bee reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for the ſaluation of mankind. Secondly, that gift of the holy ghoſt, by which any one cauſeth great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, to be amongſt the people, at his great ſignes and wonders, is very often in holy writ called by the name of faith: which not vnfitly wee may call miraculous faith: But
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27055:14"/>this faith, neither haue all the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, nor they onely: For <hi>Iohn</hi> wrought no miracles, although on the contrarie <hi>Iudas</hi> did excel therin: And with this faith, are ſometimes notably indued, and made famous, thoſe witches, deceiuers, and Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, which <hi>Rome</hi> that head of abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations both calleth Saints, and worſhippeth them alſo, with altar, praiers and Images, of whom our Sauiour hath foretold, ſaying; <hi>And they ſhall doe great wonders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; works of great power, ſo that they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue if it were poſsible the very elect.</hi> And this kinde of faith may one ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly define in this manner: namely, that it is a certaine vndoubted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, whereby one beleeueth, that God will by him doe this, or that miracle.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that the gift of the holy ghoſt, which any one receiues to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, is called by the name of Faith, and that moſt often of all the reſt: which very ſame the ſcripture calleth the Faith of God: <hi>The faith
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27055:14"/>of the ſon of God: The faith of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: The faith of Ieſus: The faith of Chriſt: and the faith of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The profeſſors of diuinitie haue ſignificantly named it Iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith. Now for this kinde of Faith, both all the Saints, and they onely haue it; for this kinde of faith, cannot befall any but ſuch as are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.</p>
            <p>This faith if wee will, wee may fitly define in this manner: Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it is a certaine full and firme confidence, engrauen by the power of the holy Ghoſt, in the heart of ſuch a one as is penitent, whereby hee aſſuredly beleeueth, that all his ſinnes are remitted, and that hee is reconciled and made one with God, in an euerlaſting loue, through Chriſt Ieſus. See, now <hi>B.</hi> this is the Faith, <hi>which ſanctifieth him that hath it,</hi> and of one miſerable maketh him <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> as it is written:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1.</note> 
               <hi>Belſſed is the man whoſe iniquities are forgiuen, and whoſe God is the Lord Iehouah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold</hi> B. this is the Faith which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27055:15"/>Iuſtifieth the wicked, and by which the Iuſtified liueth: as it is written: <hi>The iuſt ſhall liue by Faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abac.</hi> 2.4.</note> This is that faith which ouercommeth, which excelleth, and which the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine writer to the <hi>Heb.</hi> ſetteth forth with ſuch ornament, and inuironeth on euery ſide, with ſuch a multitude of praiſes: this is the faith vvhoſe worth and faireneſſe, ſo cleerely ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth throughout the ſcripture, that as it is to bee wondred, how euer it could be ſo groſſely darkned, by the vnskilfulneſſe of ſome wiſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of this our age, ſo much more maruellous is it, that the ignorance of ſuch a great benefit (eſpecially in this cleare light of all things) ſhould not hitherto, by Gods moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iudgement, be ſeuerely puniſhed.</p>
            <p>And this is that faith, concerning which is all the controuerſie this day, betwixt me, and <hi>B.</hi> which alſo the Apoſtle commendeth to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> in theſe words:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore wee conclude that a man is Iuſtified by faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:27055:15"/>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>B.</hi> is inquiring, and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching for the originall or beginning of this faith: Firſt of all he is recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vp the cauſes thereof: but hee doth that very vntowardly: for hee ſpeaketh of the Efficient cauſe, and of no more but that one. He might haue dealt more exactly in all mens iudgements, if hee had put downe all the reſt of the cauſes. But at once to rid the ſilly man of that trouble, (for as it ſeemeth he ſticketh faſt hereat:) we ſay that the matter of this faith, is a ſure, full, and vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted truſt or confidence, &amp; the forme is the fauour or grace of God the Father, and of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The efficient cauſe is the finger of God, <hi>(Viz.)</hi> the holy Ghoſt, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone imprinteth this confidence of Grace, in the hearts of the elect.</p>
            <p>The end ſubordinate is the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Saints: but the maine and cheefeſt end is, the glory of God, and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: to whom with the Father: and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27055:16"/>ſpirit one God, bleſſed for euer, be all power, praiſe &amp; honour, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all times and ages, Amen.</p>
            <p>Now then wee vnderſtand what faith is, as alſo the cauſes, and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall parts wherof it conſiſteth, (viz) <hi>Confidence or truſt, and grace or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour:</hi> Therefore let vs thus paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer theſe things: yet ſo, as although wee haue diſpatched them afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand; neuertheleſſe, wee will, that they remaine ſtill in minde, for our help in thoſe matters that follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: that wee may haue an eie as it were backe againe vnto them, as occaſion ſhall require.</p>
            <p>One thing onely is yet behinde, yet the greateſt of al, euen that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſumme of the whole contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie is placed: Namely, that wee diſcuſſe this point: How this ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious faith is wrought and ingrafted in men, and by what degrees wee muſt attaine vnto it. In the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth whereof, if our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines had walked ſo vprightly as they ought to haue done, in ſo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27055:16"/>waightie a cauſe, peraduenture wee might haue had this powerfull faith vpon earth, the true nature whereof, being now (as it were) vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt, wee doe retaine nothing of it, but the bare ſhadow onely.</p>
            <p>Firſt let vs ſee what <hi>B.</hi> holdeth concerning this point, and then wee will eſtabliſh the truth it ſelfe. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt <hi>B.</hi> goeth about to proue vnto vs the petigree (as it were) of Faith, or whence, or how it commeth: he teacheth, that the whole ſubſtance or nature thereof, ariſeth and iſſueth from three effects, or workes of the holy Ghoſt: the firſt of which (hee ſaith) is knowledge, the ſecond (as it were an increaſe of the former) he calleth aſſent, and the third (beeing the end and perfection of al the reſt) is truſt or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence. Now in aſmuch as hee ſaith, theſe are three effects or works of the holy Ghoſt, that doth hee well enough. But in this that hee teacheth them to be eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall parts of faith, therein hee is much amiſſe. But let vs diſcuſſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27055:17"/>theſe things ſeuerally and in order: This firſt worke therefore of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, <hi>B.</hi> (with moe) doth call it the gift of illumination, or the faith of knowledge: And hee teacheth that the ſame is incident to vncleane ſpirits and wicked men, into whom the <hi>Faith of Abraham can no way come.</hi> For which cauſe, I do the more exceedingly wonder at the man, that when as hee perceiued theſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring natures of Faith, and knew them to bee as ſundry ſpecials of one, and the ſame generall, and ſo diuers gifts of one and the ſame ſpirit; yet for all that, hee maketh one, an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall part of another: for indeed howſoeuer this faith of knowledge, doth neceſſarily goe before the faith of <hi>Abraham:</hi> yet doth it not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon follow that it is an eſſentiall part thereof: for many things may bee of ſuch neceſſitie, that ſome worke cannot bee diſpatched, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they be had before, yet were it a very improper ſpeech to ſay, that they be of the eſſence, or parts
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:27055:17"/>ſubſtantiall, whereof ſuch worke is made and conſiſteth; it is moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that a man ſhould be born before hee can be an Arithmeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian; is birth therefore a part of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetick? It is neceſſarie for him that will deale iuſtly, firſt of all to conſider the caſe prudently; is pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence therefore a part of Iuſtice? But euen like ſtuffe to this, is that alſo which preſently hee inferreth, in tearmes forſooth iumping trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with Ariſtotles Philoſophie: (Viz.) that the end of this good being once knowne, is to deſire it, to follow after it, and to apprehend or lay hold vpon it, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that we may ſpeake according to ſobriety: The end of this faith of knowledge, is to enioy GOD and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, euen the grace of Ieſus Chriſt; which to affirme, vvithout ſetting downe any due and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable difference; is an impious falſhood: for God vouchſafeth not this faith of knowledge to Satan, and to reprobates to this end, that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27055:18"/>he may bring them vnto his Chriſt, (viz.) to righteouſneſſe of life: But euen as the bountifulneſſe of God, doth grant the benefit, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from earth and heauen, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the fruit of that bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which is, growth and increaſe as well to the <hi>Tares,</hi> as to the <hi>Wheat,</hi> equally and indifferently; yet not to this end, that the <hi>Tares</hi> ſhould be made <hi>wheat:</hi> In like manner God very often granteth the benefit of the word, and the fruit of that bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which is to beleeue the truth, euen to thoſe that periſh: yet not to this end, that hee may ſanctifie them; but that inſomuch as they would not obey the knowne truth, which they plainely vnderſtoode, he may take vengeance vpon them in greater rigour of his Iuſtice and ſeueritie: for he that knoweth and doth not, ſhalbe beaten with more ſtripes, and to whom more is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, of him more ſhalbe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>The ſecond effect, or worke of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27055:18"/>the holy Ghoſt, <hi>B.</hi> ſometimes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth aſſent, ſometimes a certaine putting forward of the will, or a kinde of loue and good liking of this happineſſe which is offered. But what ſtrange boldneſſe is this (ô <hi>B.</hi>) that thou in things appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to God, ſhouldeſt thus pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonize, or rather play and deceiue the people of God? for the ſcripture ſpeaketh farre otherwiſe, and eal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth this 2. worke of the holie ghoſt, which is the beginning of our regeneration, by the name of <hi>Repentance,</hi> euen the thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee are prepared, to receiue the ſanctification of faith: For not one (beleeue mee) either of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, or Apoſtles, hath at any time called it aſſent, or a forward inclination of the will, or a loue of the cheefeſt good, beeing offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto vs: neither doe I thinke indeede, that any other durſt euer ſo call it, beſides thy ſelfe. I let paſſe this, that thou ſo wantonly haſt deuiſed, a twofold loue, one
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27055:19"/>called the former, which forſooth is before faith, and another tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the latter, which followeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter faith, which all of vs with one conſent doe ſay is the effect of faith, and called <hi>Loue</hi> or <hi>Charitie;</hi> But what ſhall wee ſay that former loue of thine is? B. confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that it is the very ſoule or life of faith, &amp; the trueſt difference of it that can be giuen.</p>
            <p>Becauſe (ſaith he) none can truſt in the promiſe of God, but ſuch a one as earneſtly longeth after God <hi>(viz.)</hi> by <hi>B.</hi> expoſition <hi>loueth God.</hi> Wherin he ſhamefully faileth, both in miſtaking the word, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſelfe: Hee is deceiued in the word, becauſe hee calleth this ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt longing, or deſire by the name of <hi>loue:</hi> hee erreth in the matter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee ſaith it is a part of faith: for although wee grant, that this feruent deſire, and wonderfull ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after God, muſt needs goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faith: yet wee auouch that it is no part of faith, but of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27055:19"/>as hereafter ſhalbe declared: And furthermore, to call this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, by the name of loue, proueth him to bee a moſt erroneous fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. For to ſpeake properly in things diuine, there is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, betwixt deſire and loue: for wee deſire ſuch things as wee haue not, but exceedingly faine would haue: Againe, we are ſaid in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters diuine, to loue thoſe things which wee haue already, and which wee ſeeke to enioy for euer: which points though ſome others might miſſe, yet to thee ſo great a doctor, this ſhould not haue bin vnknown: Namely, that none can loue God, vnleſſe hee bee firſt ſanctified by faith, and by that very meanes doe indeede poſſeſſe God, whom hee loueth: for vntill thou art perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in thine owne heart, that all thy ſinnes are remitted, and that thou art eternally beloued of God, thou canſt not poſſibly loue God againe, as it is written; <hi>Therefore wee loue God, becauſe hee loued vs firſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.19.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:27055:20"/>
            <p>Now it followeth, that we ſpeake of this third effect, or worke of the holy Ghoſt, which <hi>B.</hi> calleth <hi>truſt or confidence.</hi> Where that none may miſtake him, he vnderſtandeth the confidence of Grace, wherein J cannot but bewaile the wofull blindneſſe of this <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee hath placed and ſet the laſt and higheſt ſtone of our rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, before euer hee once laid the foundation of repentance; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſeeing that it is moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible, for any one, to obtaine this confidence of Grace, except hee firſt repent himſelfe of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer life, ſeriouſly and from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of his heart: for euen as the faith of knowledge, namely, to beleeue without all doubt that God is, and that hee is a rewarder of all them that doe ſeeke him in Chriſt Ieſus, and contrarily, one that taketh vengeance on all thoſe which turne away from him, for all their ſinnes and wicked deeds that euer they committed: euen (as I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:27055:20"/>ſay) this faith, muſt of neceſſitie goe before true repentance towards God: So our repentance, (viz.) that wee conuerting from our own waies vnto God, ſhould returne into the right way, muſt needs goe before the faith of Ieſus Chriſt. Therefore this is the difference, betwixt the Goſpell of God, and the Goſpell of B. The beginning of the Goſpell of God is <hi>Repentance,</hi> as it is written: <hi>The beginning</hi> of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>prepare ye the way of the Lord: (viz) performe Repentance:</hi> on the contrarie, B. beſtoweth faith vpon his elect, neuer ſo much as once na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Repentance.</hi> I can eaſily ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine why it is, namely, becauſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to fleſhly wiſedome, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſuppoſeth, that repentance is a companion of none but fooles: Therefore hee hath vtterly reiected it, as not well beſeeming the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or credit, of one that is wiſe. O vile and vngratious fellow! ſurely I can ſcarſe hold in my ſelfe, yet I will refraine. Oh wretched man (J
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27055:21"/>ſay, how dareſt thou ſo ſeditiouſlie diſturb that moſt holy order, which the wiſedome of God hath eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed? Firſt, therefore I will enforme this erroneous doctor, that true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance towards God, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, goe before the faith of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: Then what this true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance towards GOD is, ſhall likewiſe in order be declared.</p>
            <p>But to the end, that theſe things more clearely may bee vnderſtoode, it behooueth vs, not onely to call to minde, thoſe things which haue bin aboueſaid, but to make ſomewhat a further repetition of the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>The firſt benefit therefore which God vouchſafeth (I ſpeake onely of thoſe bleſſings, which pertaine to ſaluation) is the ſeede and miniſtery of the Word: vnto this outward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, and miniſterie of the Word, there is ſometimes added a certaine inward vertue, and efficacie of the holy ghoſt, who as he leaueth ſome in vnbeliefe: ſo he inclineth others,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27055:21"/>and cauſeth them to cleaue faſt vnto the truth, with the whole aſſent of their minds, and to beleeue it: And this kind of faith, (becauſe it is a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie or barren exerciſe of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding only) wee call the faith of knowledge: and ſuch like, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; becauſe they profeſſe the faith of Chriſt, we call by a common and generall name, Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Now after this the holy ghoſt, cauſing his wheele as it were to run about the ſecond time, goeth to his worke againe, and of thoſe vvhich are beleeuers, ſome hee reformeth and maketh new creatures, others he reſerueth to their more iuſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, becauſe the truth which they knew they obeied not. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe generall Chriſtians, and thoſe which bee regenerated, there is no leſſe difference, then betwixt the Altar and the Temple, the Sanctuarie and the Porch: betwixt him, the foreskin of whoſe heart is circumciſed, and him, whoſe houſe onely is cleane ſwept and garniſhed:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27055:22"/>(viz.) as betwixt thoſe that are bid to the ſupper of the lambs marriage, and thoſe which are without, <hi>Dogs, Witches, Couetous, Murderers, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, and ſuch as take pleaſure in lies.</hi> But in the reforming of theſe, or making them new creatures, the holy Ghoſt obſerueth this order.</p>
            <p>Firſt, hee mollifieth or ſoftneth them, and cauſeth them to bewaile their ſinnes, and by earneſt praier to make ſure for pardon, and with reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and vnſpeakeable deſire, to ſeek the fauour of that GOD, whom without all reaſon they haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And this is that ſecond effect or worke of the holy Ghoſt, which is the beginning of our regeneration: which B. himſelfe calleth the ſecond effect of the ſpirit: but hee is ſo far from teaching the ſame perfectly, that hee doth not ſo much as name it rightly: for hee calleth it a certain motion or action of the will, vnfitly and philoſophically. The ſcripture contrarily calleth it repentance, which is not onely a certaine moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:27055:22"/>of the will, but a full change al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together of the whole man: vvhen that which before was pleaſant and delightfull to the ſinner, is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come nothing but greefe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of heart, vnto him: when that which before hee chiefely ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, now hee moſt of all abhoireth: and whereas formerly he reioiced in his falling from God, now he incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly ſeeketh, intreateth, thirſteth, longeth, euen as the Hart panteth, after the riuers of water: deſiring to haue his tedious thirſt ſatisfied. To this man now, like a woman vvith child, labouring of ſorrow; the holy Ghoſt doth the third time reach forth his hand, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth vnto him comforts, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the multitude of his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows: and vpon the heart of this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and trembling penitent, that confidence of grace which wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after, is imprinted by the ſame Spirit: whereby he aſſuredly belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, that all his ſinnes which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed him ſo, are now forgiuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27055:23"/>him; and that God, whoſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and fauour, hee once ſo greatly longed after, now beareth good wil and hath a loue vnto him, not onely for the preſent, but for euer. And this is that third effect or worke of the holy ghoſt, (viz.) the ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith; which finiſheth or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vp our regeneration, which B. himſelfe alſo calleth the third ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the Spirit: and which he ſo much endeauoureth to commend vnto his hearers, miſerablie beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it (as it were) from other mens coffers.</p>
            <p>This is Gods ſtedfaſt and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table order, whereof hee will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repent, nor change it for euer. Hereof giueth he aſſurance vnto all, by his owne teſtimonie, who alone is aſmuch as all other; being a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full witneſſe, and Lord ouer all; who preaching his own kingdome to men, in expreſſe words ſpeaketh after this manner:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Repent and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the goſpel.</hi> Likewiſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle being ſent forth to preach, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27055:23"/>forth: they admoniſh all men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where to repent: Repentance is it indeede, which in the firſt place they euer proclaimed, for hereby as by a ladder, wee muſt aſcend to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The ſame Apoſtle, when the Iewes asked,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37.38.</note> 
               <hi>Men and brethren what ſhall wee doe: Peter</hi> anſwered, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and bee baptiſed in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, for the remiſsion of ſins.</hi> And good reaſon, becauſe the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of the holy ghoſt, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, can bee vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to none but ſuch as repent.</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth thoſe which murdered the Lord of life, <hi>to repent and bee conuerted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>that your iniquities</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>maybe done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> And very rightly: for no mans ſinne can bee taken away, vnleſſe hee repent, and bee conuerted. <hi>Iſay</hi> thus prophecieth concerning the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.1.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord is vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, that I ſhould preach the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, (viz.) The ioy full and happie em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage of the free grace, &amp; fauour of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27055:24"/>God, for Chriſts ſake to bee vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed.</hi> But vpon whom? <hi>To the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, the poore, the broken, (viz.) The penitent:</hi> for the kingdome of heauen pertaineth to none; <hi>but the humble, the poore, the lowly, &amp; little ones:</hi> (viz.) <hi>The penitent.</hi> Stayeſt thou ſtil? whileſt I ouerſway thee with the authoritie of the ſcriptures, art thou not rather amazed, that theſe things ſhould either bee vnknowne or denied of ſuch a one as thou art? To goe a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle further, I will demand this one thing of thee: wherfore I pray thee did the Lord giue ſuch an honorable teſtimonie of his ſeruant <hi>Iohn,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring, Namely,<note place="margin">Luke <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that hee was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, yea and more then a Prophet: and that amongſt all the ſonnes of women, there was not his greater?</hi> Beware thou anſwere not with Babylon, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe hee was neuer maried, or for his auſtere and hard kinde of liuing, leſt thou make the vvhole cope of heauen, laugh at thy folly. Why ſtickeſt thou at it man? I will rid thee of this trouble: it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27055:24"/>for the dignitie and neceſſity of his miniſtery: and the miniſterie of <hi>Iohn,</hi> was the baptiſme of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, wherewith except a man bee firſt waſhed, hee can by no meanes put on Chriſt; for which cauſe, the Prophet calleth <hi>Iohn;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Jſai.</hi> 40.3.</note> 
               <hi>The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner, appointed to prepare the ways of the Lord:</hi> for in very truth, euen as a field is not fit for ſeede, vnleſſe it be tilled, ſo the hearts of ſinners, are neuer made ready &amp; prepared to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the promiſe of faith, but by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; as it were by diuine and heaueniy tillage. And that thou maiſt neuer make more doubt, but know paſt queſtion, that this is both the ordinance of God, and alſo euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; heare what the Baptiſer himſelf ſpeaketh: <hi>I</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>baptiſe you with water. With the water,</hi> namely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 3.16</note> of <hi>regeneration</hi> (viz.) with <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. But hee that commeth after, ſhal baptiſe you with the Spirit and with fire: (viz.) ſhall ſanctifie you vvith faith.</hi> Therefore Faith meeteth or taketh a place with Repentance,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:27055:25"/>that hath bin before it; for by theſe two only, is made of a ſinner a new creature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3.5.</note> as it is written: <hi>Except a man be borne againe of water and the Spirit, hee cannot enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</hi> Yea but I, ſaieſt thou, do not ſo vnderſtand theſe things. And ſaieſt thou ſo indeede? Thou ſo great a man: Dector of the chaire, that as it were, letteſt out to farme thy learning in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, teaching from an higher place heauenly matters, and yet vnderſtandeſt not earthly, and ſuch as are farre beneath the chaire: for ſo our Sauiour calleth theſe principles and rudiments, as it were, or firſt beginnings of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie.</p>
            <p>But let vs diſpatch that vvhich remaineth, and conſider, what this true repentance towards GOD is indeed. Concerning the name ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in another place may bee ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: Now wee will inſiſt vpon the thing it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Wee ſay therefore, that repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27055:25"/>is an effectuall operation of the holy Ghoſt, whereby a man returneth from his owne waies, and conuerteth himſelfe vnto GOD. Now to returne from his owne waies, is to bewaile his ſinnes, and the tranſgreſſions of his life, in which as in wandring pathes hee hath gone aſtray. Wherefore his returning, comprehendeth the mollifying of his heart, or contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and to bee conuerted vnto God, is to confeſſe our ſinnes vnto God, and moſt earneſtly to ſeeke peace, and reconciliation with him: Therefore conuerſion vnto God conteineth in it, confeſſion, deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and praying againſt the offence, and a certaine incredible deſire, or longing after Peace.</p>
            <p>Requireſt thou further proofe B. of this repentance? looke then vpon that prodigall, and forlorne ſonne, of a very exceeding good Father: in whoſe example our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour teacheth, both thee and mee, and all ſinners what to doe.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:27055:26"/>
            <p>Hearken therefore, what the Lord ſaith concerning him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.17.</note> 
               <hi>But when</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hee came to himſelfe,</hi> (viz.) When be was returned from his owne waies, which was by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking himſelfe more ſeriouſlie, how raſhly and vnaduiſedly he had dealt in ſinning againſt God his moſt bountifull and kinde father, then was hee in an vtter diſlike of himſelfe, and with a broken heart, he ſorrowed amaine continually.</p>
            <p>Thus haſt thou his contrition: Now liſten after what manner hee conuerteth himſelfe vnto God: <hi>I will returne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.18</note> ſaith he, <hi>vnto my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> There thou haſt his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Now hearken further, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion hee maketh vnto his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>And I will ſay vnto him, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I haue finned againſt heauen, and before thee, and am no more worthy to be called thine.</hi> In this thou haſt the guilty confeſſing his fault, with deteſtation of it, and ſtrong re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts againſt it, knocking his wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27055:26"/>breſt in rufull manner, with his guilty hand.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, hearken vnto his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible deſire of Peace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation: <hi>Make me as one of thy hired ſeruants:</hi> as if hee ſhould ſay, <hi>Returne vnto mee (O my God) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue me: though now vnworthy the name of a ſonne, yet ſet mee in the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of one of thy hired ſeruants, yea, make mee the leaſt and loweſt of thy ſeruants, ſo thou make me thine at all.</hi> Heere is his vnſpeakeable longing after God. Perceiueſt thou (ô B.) how this man is now prepared in heart, and how much he is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from that hee was before?</p>
            <p>Being deſcended of an high and honourable race, hee now taketh vnto him a low and baſe eſtate; being before of manly ſtomacke, now hee ſits downe among the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children: being before hard and ſtubborne, now is become ſoft as water. And further (beleeue mee) the mountaine doth not more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the valley: the crooked
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:27055:27"/>from the ſtraight: the ragged from the ſmooth: the diſcreetly aged, from the little child: the hard flint, from the ſoft and tender wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Theſe I ſay differ not from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, more then this man now from that hee was in time paſt: and this is the right order and manner of true and vnfained repentance. <hi>Oh happy and bleſſed man,</hi> indeede be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all compare, who can vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, and doe thereafter. But hitherto haue I lightly contended, by a general kinde of diſcourſing, with this cragged and cloudie ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſter: for if I ſhould ſtand vpon euery particular, there would bee no end of reprehenſions: for it is incredible to be told, how often he ſtumbleth and miſſeth: taking Faith for Repentance, and likewiſe Repentance for Faith, whereby he euidently declareth vnto vs, his groſſe ignorance of both:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 19.20.</note> He hath not ſo much as made any mention of Repentance, in that place, where it ſhould eſpecially haue beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:27055:27"/>of: at the laſt he puts it after faith, or rather hee ſaith, it is faith it ſelfe: which ſurely hee ought in no caſe to haue done, foraſmuch chiefely as God himſelfe, both in his eternall counſell, &amp; vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able order, hath diſtinguiſhed theſe each from other: for Repentance is the firſt beginning, and as it were the entrie of our regeneration: (viz.) the effectuall working of the holy Ghoſt: wherby a ſinner com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to himſſelfe againe, doth moſt earneſtly ſeeke after nothing elſe at the hand of GOD, but to haue his ſinnes pardoned, and to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into his fauour.</p>
            <p>But faith is the very perfection, &amp; as it were the higheſt top of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation: <hi>(viz.)</hi> The inſculpture or engrauing of the holy Ghoſt: whereby the repentant doth aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly beleeue, that all his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are forgiuen, and his ſinnes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and that hee is vnited with God in an euerlaſting loue, through Ieſus Chriſt onely.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:27055:28"/>
            <p>I might now performe a worke perhaps, well worth my paines, if I ſhould here declare what bee the fruits of this excellent faith, that ſo might be obſerued concerning this ſanctified &amp; regenerate man, whom the holy Ghoſt, with ſuch great induſtrie, and ſpeciall care hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and brought foorth; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what a one hee is within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and at home: but alſo what are his works abroad, and in open ſight. But becauſe B. hath altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther omitted this point, wee alſo will deferre to ſpeake of it, vntill ſome other time. Now when his hearers were ready to depart, hee puts one queſtion more vnto them: (viz.) whether this faith doe by the worthineſſe of it ſelf iuſtifie a man ot not. Wherein hee is ſo tedious that hee cloies them all: ſeeing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry children can tell that theſe kinds of ſpeeches are all figuratiue, and there is in them the Metonymia of the cauſe: For the ſcripture when it teacheth that a man is iuſtified
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:27055:28"/>by faith, meaneth by the figure hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pallagie, that a man is iuſtified by the grace of Ieſus Chriſt, which is reuealed through Faith: which kinde of ſpeaking is moſt vſuall, euen amongſt the vulgar ſort, as to ſay, <hi>Philoctetes</hi> liued by his bow and arrowes, <hi>Orpheus</hi> by his Harp, <hi>Zeuxis</hi> by his pencill; when as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe it is vnderſtood, that they by theſe inſtruments of their artes and trades, did get ſuch things as vvere requiſite for their vſe, and for the maintenance of their liues.</p>
            <p>We haue already accompliſhed, as I ſuppoſe, the firſt part of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe: wee haue ſet forth the true faith of Ieſus Chriſt; wee haue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore ſhewed the true cauſes and parts thereof, and after vvhat manner it is wrought, and brought to paſſe in men. Moreouer, wee haue declared what true repentance towards God is, and that the ſame neceſſarily before faith, and by the eternall ordinance of God, in the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:27055:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>new making of a ſinner, and that faith doth of neceſſitie follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter repentance, yet not by debt, but by grace, not for the worthineſſe of him that hath repented, but for the fidelitie of him that hath promiſed, according to that which is written:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze</hi> 18.28.</note> 
               <hi>As often as a ſinner repenteth of his ſinnes, as I liue</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I wil blot out his iniquities, &amp;c.</hi> That the inheritance might alwaies be giuen by promiſe, as teſtifieth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, ſaying:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>But God gaue the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance to Abraham, freely by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus briefely, haue wee followed B. vpon the ſaying of <hi>Paul: that a man is iuſtified by faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28.</note> It remaineth that we ſee whether this Juſtifying faith, bee commanded in the lawe, yea or no: Vpon the words of this verſ. 28. <hi>VVithout the workes of the Lawe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ful and perfect explanation of which words, B. by a fiue fold que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, ſeemeth to himſelfe notably to haue performed. And firſt he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:27055:29"/>whether the workes of the lawe, are of force to attain the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God, and anſwereth, that they are ſo, as they proceede from faith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, whereas the workes of the lawe done by faith iuſtifie; hee anſwereth with <hi>Auſten,</hi> that indeed they doe not iuſtifie, but follow him that is iuſtified.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, whereas the workes of the lawe done by faith, be neceſſarie to ſaluation; hee anſwereth that they are neceſſarie to ſaluation, but not for Iuſtification. And leſt this new vpſtart copulation, of workes of the lawe and faith, ſhould trouble any (which the Apoſtle euery where, and here eſpecially oppoſeth as contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) hee enquireth in the 4. place, whether faith may be ſaid in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, to bee commanded in the law: and anſwereth readily that it is. And hee labours in the laſt place, to explaine the reaſon of this expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>Paul</hi> maketh between faith and the lawe.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:27055:30"/>
            <p>Wee will firſt ſee what this vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator of the lawe hath diſordered in the fourth place: for this decided, his ignorance in making the other doubt, will bee euident to any: for in this point alone, as in a hinge, all the waight of the other difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties is turned, and in theſe things we will follow our owne order: firſt wee will confute B. afterwards forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the truth.</p>
            <p>B. firſt reaſon then, whereby hee goeth about to proue, that faith is required in the lawe, is drawne out of theſe words of the lawe: <hi>I am thy God</hi> that is, as this Gloſſographiſt and ſubtill Sophiſter interprets it; <hi>I onely will be thy God, and thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſhalt put thy whole confidence, and hope of ſaluation in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here therefore, (ſaith he,) is faith commanded. As if, B. theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounes, Mine, Thine, are notes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies and neceſſarily of a fatherly power, and not rather of Lordſhip and ſuperioritie. What authoritie is this? Or what are you? haue you
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:27055:30"/>power ouer words, that thus make and marre them at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure?</p>
            <p>But you ſay: Not I only, but many learned men before mee; <hi>Melanct. Martyr,</hi> and other. As if it skilled, whether you, of your owne accord, and of your ſelfe erred, or follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other, ſuffer your ſelfe to bee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, euen as cattle goe headlong after the flocks of cattle going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them.</p>
            <p>The 2. reaſon of <hi>B.</hi> is thus fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. All pietie towards God is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Decalogu: but in faith onely, all pietie is conteined: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faith only is commanded in the lawe. Here this <hi>Proteus</hi> doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude vs by ambiguitie: for if by all pietie towards God, hee ineane all thoſe duties of godlineſſe, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the perfect righteouſneſſe of the lawe, (viz). the righteouſneſſe of workes, then his propoſition is true, and agreeing to the maieſtie of the Lawe: but his aſſumption is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly falſe: for faith, neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teines,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:27055:31"/>nor performes that ſpirituall obedience of the lawe, (viz.) the righteouſneſſe of workes, for it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, it onely laies hold vpon the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God, (viz.) the grace of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Wherby it no leſſe attaines the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, then if hee had perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the ſpirituall righteouſneſſe of the law. But if by all pietie towards GOD, hee vnderſtand all thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of pietie, which the faithfull (their nature being now ſold vnder ſinne) doe performe from faith, and that no other obedience is required in the lawe, beſides this of faith: if this hee hold, I ſay, then his propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is erroneous, &amp; no leſſe oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the maieſtie of the lawe, then is the furtheſt part of the Eaſt, to the vttermoſt corner of the Weſt: for the decalogu requireth that piety of the faithfull, which none of them can fulfill: neither doth it by the righteous ſentence thereof, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne that righteous man that fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth 7. times a day, leſſe, then any
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:27055:31"/>wicked one that neuer beleeued, for the lawe is deliuered to the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and tranſgreſſor, not to this, or that particular, but to all, of what mould ſo euer thou art made, that ſinneſt, of what ſtock, vertue, pietie, ſaith: in what fauour with God it paſſeth not; if thou fault neuer ſo little, it adiudgeth thee to death; for the lawe of the decalogue is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall lawe; contrariwiſe euery one, euen the moſt holy is ſold vnder ſin, and ſo, that if God had not found out another lawe of grace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, by which hee might freelie giue the inheritance, to holy <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his ſeede; then bleſſed <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaak</hi> ſhould aſwel haue been diſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited, as abiect <hi>Iſmael;</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> beloued had periſhed with <hi>Eſau</hi> that was hated. What then, wil ſome ſay, is God vniuſt, that hath giuen ſuch a law to men, as none can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme? God forbid. What? is God vnrighteous, becauſe thou art wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked? made hee not thee holy, and graced thee with that perfection,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:27055:32"/>that thou mighteſt eaſily if thou wouldeſt, performe thoſe things which the lawe commandeth: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, thou wittingly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, caſts thy ſelfe headlong into ſuch a forlorne eſtate, as that novv thou art vtterly vnable to pay the debt. I will ſomewhat aſſwage the ſadneſſe of this argument, by the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of a ſimilitude. A certaine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter committed to two of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, 1000. peeces of ſiluer, vpon a bill at a certaine day; in the meane ſpace, the ſeruants through idleneſſe abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in riot &amp; exceſſe waſted al: The day comes, the maſter calls one of them, ſheweth the bill, requires the ſiluer. The ſeruant on the other ſide confeſſeth the bill of his hand, but ſaith that all the money is ſpent, and accuſeth his maſter of vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifulneſſe and cruelty, becauſe hee doth ſo hardly exact a 1000. pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſiluer, of a poore miſerable man, that hath not one penny to pay. To whom his maſter (wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at the ſhameleſſe boldneſſe of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:27055:32"/>the man) anſweres: Aske I thee any thing but mine owne? may I not by right require of thee, that which freely and of my owne bounty, I put into thy hands? am I vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, becauſe thou art riotous, or am I cruell, becauſe thou art pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall? So his maſter angerly bids that hee be carried to priſon, there to bee puniſhed, and takes a great oath, he ſhall not come from thence till hee haue paide the vttermoſt farthing. Alſo hee cals for his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, with whom after the ſame manner, hee deales by his bill. But hee beeing priuie to his riot and prodigalitie, quakes euery ioint, and hanging down his head (ſaith) I acknowledge the bill indeed, and confeſſe all the debt to bee due. But my ſinne hath brought mee to that extremitie of miſery, that I am not able to diſcharge it: ô ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter haue pitie on mee, (ſaith hee) and weeping falleth at his feete. This was the controuerſie: This alſo is the iſſue of it. Now B. bee
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:27055:33"/>Iudge your ſelfe: for this Lord and maſter dreadeth not to commit his matter to any vmpire. Nay I thinke there can ſcarce any debtor bee found, ſo impudent and paſt ſhame that durſt ſpeake in this manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any couetous, baſe lawe-breaking vſurer, as that wicked minded debtor, and deſperat ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrift ſpoke againſt his maſter.</p>
            <p>But B. goeth on, God, ſaith hee, would firſt of all haue his people beleeue in him, which is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall part of religion: Therefore it followes, that hee commanded them faith, in his moſt perfect law. ô poore &amp; blind co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience! as if for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, hee had not from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning giuen another law, (viz,) of promiſe and life, no leſſe perfect, then this moſt perfect law of the Decalogue: whereby he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his people to beleeue, &amp; place all their affiance in him. Here then by the doubtfull termes of the lawe, hee deludes both himſelfe and others: for God in this Decalogue
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:27055:33"/>hath inioined that righteouſneſſe to vs alone, which the worthineſſe of the worker obtaineth, as it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>The man that doth theſe things ſhal liue in them.</hi> But by the lawe of grace, he hath firſt, twice, thrice, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies commended to vs that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which is onely obtained, by the faith of the beleeuers, as it is written: <hi>Hee that beleeueth in him, ſhall not be aſhamed.</hi> But B. ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes to ſpeake perplexedly. If, ſaith hee, God haue not commanded faith in the law, why hath hee comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded other things, which without faith are vaine &amp; friuolous? I would know B. what you meane by this word, Other things: meane you the ceremonies? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maſter Doctor you diſpute not the point: for the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie is not of the ceremoniall, but of the moral law: for we know, and euery one doth thinke (except I bee deceiued) that the law is Synec. vſed for the ceremonies, that was our ſchoolmaſter to Chriſt, and that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it ſet not out Chriſt in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:27055:34"/>tearmes, yet in obſcurer ſort it ſhadowed him out. But if by that word, Other things, you vnderſtand the duties of all the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Decalogue; then are you preſſed downe by the ſame waight that you were before: for not onely the worke that we do without faith, but alſo the actions of ſin that proceed from faith, are vaine and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous, yea hatefull to God, if they be brought to that perfect righteouſnes of the ten commandements: for the legall righteouſnes is ſpiritual, (viz.) it taxeth thee, not onely for the fact, but for the inward luſt.</p>
            <p>This wicked and faithleſſe man is a man-flaier: thou a St. &amp; beleeuer art angry: The law of God condemnes you both for it, commandeth not to kill: wherein hee forbiddeth as wel anger, as murther: This wicked and faithleſſe man, altogether deſolate, giueth himſelf ouer to whoredome, and reioiceth in it. Thou being holy and a beleeuer, art ſet at liberty from the dominion of luſt, as from a rude
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:27055:34"/>and impious miſtris, now hateſt and flieſt all the enticements thereof, but yet thou haſt ſome affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereto, remaining and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt the gouernment of the ſpirit: The law condemnes both: for it hath ſaid to him; <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie:</hi> to thee, <hi>thou ſhalt not luſt.</hi> O thou diſſembler and heartleſſe doctor, if thou ſeeſt not theſe things: a trifler, if thou do.</p>
            <p>But B. goes on. If, ſaith he, GOD hath not commanded faith in the law, hee commands hypocriſie. O wickedneſſe worthy to be caried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to bee wondred at! Whence come you B? I maruell. What from <hi>Rome?</hi> ſeeing you dare ſo without feare, caſt out againſt God, the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of your raſhnes. With how much fairer a forehead, might you haue made theſe diſtributions of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Either GOD hath commanded faith in the Decalogue, or perfect righteouſnes: but not this, therefore that. But now you aſſume that which is falſer then falſhood it ſelfe. So
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:27055:35"/>that neither you, nor the very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all ſubtiltie, can euer bee able to proue it. But B. proceeds in his troubled ſpeech. Chriſt, ſaith hee, is propounded to vs in the law: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faith is commanded in the law. The Antecedent he ſtrengthens by two reaſons; the firſt is this; There is often mention made (ſaith hee) of the Meſſias in the law, and a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſhadowing out, and repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, and his oblations in the waſhings, and ſacrifices: Therefore Chriſt is ſet forth in the lawe. I would wonder truely, if that you would vtter any word in truth, with an honeſt minde: for hereby alſo as you are wont, you delude vs with ambiguitie, for the antecedent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the law of the ceremonies, wherof there is no controuerſie that I know: for with one mouth, all doe confeſſe that it was inſtituted to that end, to informe that people to the righteouſnes of God, (viz. the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, and that not ſo dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but the ceremoniall lawe may
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:27055:35"/>more rightly bee called a Goſpell, then a lawe: contrariwiſe, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the lawe doth deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thruſt vpon vs the decalogue: So that he expounds one thing, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes another, that though the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent bee true, yet the concluſion is falſe. But B. ſeeing this firſt ioin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of no force, doth againe ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the matter, and deales with God by the ſealed tables.</p>
            <p>For (ſaith hee) when God ſaith hee is thy God, which brought thee out of Egypt: doth hee not ſet forth himſelfe as a Redeemer? But hee is not a Redeemer but in Chriſt. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore incluſiuely Chriſt is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to vs in theſe words. Here B. if I would obiect their iudgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, as the <hi>Treach</hi> of the <hi>Alpes,</hi> who ſay that in euery perfect lawe, three things are to be obſerued. Firſt, the preface, whereby hee maketh his Auditors attentiue: Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby hee biddeth a thing to bee done, or left vndone: Thirdly, correction, whereby he denounceth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:27055:36"/>puniſhment, to the delinquent. Here (I ſay) if as they doe, that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed with ſubtill deceits (that with the very names of theſe men, as with legions brought out, I could put you to flight) I ſhould ſay that theſe words of the law: <hi>Heare O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, I am the Lord thy God, that brought thee out of the land of Egypt;</hi> were onely a preface of the lawe, and as it were a commendation of the future ſpeech, ſhould I not ſtop thy mouth and thy fellowes, except you were refractarie?</p>
            <p>But I will not wound you, with other mens darts: but rather out of my own, thus I anſwer: though God ſaith, he is their deliuerer, touching this priuate bondage, he doth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently propound Chriſt to them, and the benefit of this deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. But this is his meaning afore all things: That <hi>Iſrael</hi> might neuer put out of minde, the memorie of ſo great a benefit, and the authour thereof. Take heede that you doe not barke againe, as if J ſhould ſay,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:27055:36"/>that this Egyptian deliuerance, doth heere typically ſignifie, the ſpirituall deliuerance of mans bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: only, I affirme, that God hath not vnfolded to his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> neither his Chriſt, nor his deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>Theſe are, if I be not deceiued, all the deceits of B Which, that they might haue more waight of deceite, hee hath alſo added mens Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: <hi>M. &amp; N.</hi> for he thought that he ſhould not procure to himſelfe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient credit, by his owne proper and domeſticall engines, and inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, except hee vndertooke the patronage of forren errors, taken to them. Howſoeuer one may fitly thus interpret <hi>N.</hi> that he thought ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoberly and godly, if you reſpect the righteouſnes of the lawe: (viz.) the righteouſnes of workes. But if hee meane the righteouſnes of God, which is of faith, I think he hath erred with you; if either hee thought that God would exact al the pietie, which the regenerate performe to God by
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:27055:37"/>faith: according to this rule of the Decalogue, or hee that appointed none, or enioined other works to the faithfull any where, then that which agreeth to the righteouſnes of this law, as to the rule.</p>
            <p>But this our labor, ſeemes a little to take breath. Now after it hath come out of the ſtarting holes of B. as out of writhen turnings of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth, that which is behinde wee ſhall more pleaſantly paſſe. Truth I hope being my companion.</p>
            <p>All the errour of <hi>B.</hi> then conſiſts herein, that hee hath not diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the law of life, from the Morall lawe: which yet God in his eternall counſell, and preſcript words, euen from the beginning hath ſeuered, with as great a diſtance one from another, as <hi>Hager</hi> differs from <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra:</hi> bondage from liberty, <hi>Sina</hi> from <hi>Sion.</hi> But now <hi>B.</hi> I ſee thee like a fearefull Marriner, to foreſee the tempeſt, comming a farre off: and to dread the Shipwrack of thine error. Now when I ſpeake of the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:27055:37"/>Law of life, I meane the promiſe which was giuen to <hi>Adam</hi> in theſe words,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall breake his heade, &amp;c.</hi> Jt was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched afterward to <hi>Abraham: In thee ſhall all the Nations of the earth be bleſſed:</hi> againe,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Looke to heauen and count, if thou canſt, the number of the Starres; ſo ſhall thy ſeed be.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> At laſt it was deliuered by <hi>Moſes: Heare ô Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord our God is one God, thou ſhalt loue the Lord with all thy heart, &amp;c.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12</note> 
               <hi>Now ô Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, what doth the Lord thy God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of thee, but that thou feare the Lord thy God and honour him, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that Law whereof the ſame <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaieth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.19</note> 
               <hi>Behold I ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you bleſſing and curſing, Life and good, death and euill, &amp;c. Bleſſing and life, if thou chuſe this,</hi> viz. <hi>If thou loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> If thou chuſe this (ſaith he) <hi>Bleſſed ſhalt thou be at home, and bleſſed abrode, &amp;c.</hi> But contrariwiſe (ſaith he) <hi>If thou wilt not be obedient to the voice of the Lord thy God, to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:27055:38"/>keepe and doe the Commandements of this Law, curſed ſhalt thou bee at home and curſed abroad, &amp;c.</hi> Behold <hi>B.</hi> the Law, the moſt high and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect publiſhing whereof, when the Prophet foreſaw, thus ſaid, <hi>The Law ſhall goe foorth of Sion, and the word of the Lord out of Ieruſalem.</hi> He ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not of the Law of the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue which was come out moſt perfectly, 700. yeeres before: but this Law of life, (viz.) <hi>The word of truth,</hi> (viz.) <hi>The Goſpell</hi> Behold the Law, of which the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>I will write my Law in their hearts.</hi> Not that of the tenne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, which is to bee trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at, <hi>He that doth theſe things ſhall line by them:</hi> but this Law of life and the promiſe, <hi>I will bee their God, and they ſhall be my people, and I will remember their ſinnes no more, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Behold the law, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the true ſpeaking King and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Law of the Lord is perfect euery way, conuerting ſoules, &amp;c.</hi> Hee meanes not <hi>B.</hi> that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:27055:38"/>Law of the Decalogue, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be the Law of God, and a Law euery way perfect, yet doth not conuert ſoules, neither can it giue life nor reſtore a ſinner. But he meanes this Law of grace, <hi>viz.</hi> The promiſe and righteouſneſſe of God, by the faith of the Meſſias, which is giuen to the beleeuer.</p>
            <p>Behold <hi>B.</hi> the law wherein faith is commanded, for none can loue God with all his heart, and his neighbour as himſelfe, but he that firſt is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith, <hi>viz.</hi> none but he that is waſhed before, by vertue of the holy ghoſt, ſhal <hi>beleeue that al his ſins are forgiuen him.</hi> Hoe, ſaith <hi>B.</hi> what newes bring you here? for that which you cal the Law of grace, we ſay it is the ſame with the law of the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. What expoſition is this? will you thus inwrap the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, with your expoſition? Dare you ſay, this is the ſame Law with that, when God himſelfe ſaith, it is another from it?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.31.</note> 
               <hi>For behold the daies come</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>that I will
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:27055:39"/>make a new couenant with the houſe of Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>not ſuch as I made with your Fathers, &amp;c.</hi> Hitherto leades the Teſtimony of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that ſo cleare as if it were written with the beames of the Sunne, (which yet this Oule ſees not.) Who when hee had deliuered this Law of life to <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and had added Ceremonies, which were as a ſhadowing out of a Redeemer; at length breathing out ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut</hi> 29.1.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe are the words of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which the Lord commanded Moſes, that he ſhould make with the children of Iſrael in the land of Moab, beſides that couenant which hee made in the mount Horeb.</hi> And that the law of the Decalogue, and the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of it which is of workes, is not onely another from, but alſo oppoſit to the law of grace and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God, which is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by faith; the Apoſtle is a moſt plentifull witneſſe, who calleth the law of the Decalogue, <hi>A weake Law: the Law of ſinne, the Law of death, the miniſtry of condemnation.</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:27055:39"/>But the law of grace, hee cals <hi>the power of God vnto ſaluation: The righteouſneſſe of God, the miniſtrie of the ſpirit, the miniſtrie of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But hoe, will ſome ſay, <hi>Paul</hi> is a meere Maniche, and a manifeſt Marcionite, that thus detracts from the maieſty of the Law, and ſo odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly inueies againſt the holy Law of God. Saieſt thou ſo, dog? is the Apoſtle an Hereticke, becauſe thou art blind. Thou conceiueſt not the truth of his words: for hee hath not brought in this combat of the law, either in reſpect of God, or the lawes themſelues, for both are of, and from, the ſame God. both perfect, holy, and iuſt: but in reſpect of vs, and our ſinne; for what ſo repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and hoſtile, as to condemne a ſinner, and to abſolue the ſame? Therefore as we are wont to call, a day deadly or fatall, not in reſpect of the day it ſelfe, but of them which muſt vndergoe ſome danger: And the Iulian law of Treaſon, we call a deadly law in reſpect of them that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:27055:40"/>are accuſed of Treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: So the Apoſtle cals the law of the Deca. <hi>a weake law,</hi> becauſe it cannot giue life to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>The law of wrath,</hi> becauſe it cauſeth wrath againſt ſin. The law of ſin, becauſe it accuſeth vs of ſin. <hi>The law of death,</hi> becauſe it iudgeth vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bound ouer to death. <hi>The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> becauſe it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth euery tranſgreſſion. In which phraſe of ſpeech hee calleth alſo the Goſpel it ſelfe, ſometimes the ſauour <hi>of death vnto death,</hi> namely, in reſpect of thoſe that periſh.</p>
            <p>But <hi>B.</hi> opinion, gaſping at laſt, doth yet throw one dart more: if (ſaith he) the righteouſnes of the law, be ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the righteouſneſſe of God, which is of faith, how doth faith eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it? This I ſay, <hi>B.</hi> Chriſt and his righteouſnes is giuen to vs, who are iuſtified by faith: now the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt is the righteouſnes of works, <hi>viz.</hi> the ful &amp; perfect perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Decalogue. To vs then that are in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>viz.</hi> to vs that beleeue in him, who hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:27055:40"/>the righteouſneſſe of the law for vs, it is as much to vs as if we our ſelues had fulfilled it. For the end of the law is to iuſtifie the keeper of it: but he that beleeueth in him, who hath perfectly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>it, this faith ſhall bee imputed to him for righteouſnes,</hi> no leſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if he had perfectly performed the ſame.</p>
            <p>But let vs proceed, and purſue this breathleſſe opinion, euen to the ſepulchre: which in a manner dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp; cannot caſt darts, doth yet caſt out words. To what end then, ſaith he, ſerueth the law: or what vſe is there of it now? I ſay, much, euery way: firſt, it is ſet downe for the ſinner, both that hee may not deny the puniſhment, denounced againſt him for ſinne, and alſo that it may take vengeance againſt him iuſtly for the ſame: it is alſo ſet for a holy and regenerate man, that as often as he looke vpon it (and alwaies hee ought to looke vpon it) hee may ſo often bewaile his wickedneſſe, and quake at it; and likewiſe as often as
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:27055:41"/>he cals to minde, which night and day hee ought to call to minde: ſo often hee may thinke, of the riches, mercy, and loue of God, by giuing him thanks by Chriſt Ieſus his Lord and interceſſor, who ſo mercifully hath ſet him free from the wrath of this iuſt and holy law. Nothing that I know is now omitted: Let vs therefore take breath awhile; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeeing we haue gone ſo far, and come as it were to the ſepulchre of this dead and ſpiritleſſe opinion, which whiles it is caſt into obliuion, as into the fire, and while the buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all is attended; I will turne me to <hi>B.</hi> and by a certaine compariſon, as much as I can, I will comfort him, leſt he without comfort lament the death of his opinion, as of a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dearely beloued: and if any ſenſe be left in him, I will labour to make him ſound minded. A certaine king hath many debters, indebted vnto him, for much money by writing; whereby it is prouided that except they faithfully pay all the mony at
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:27055:41"/>the day appointed, their goods ſhould be confiſcate and themſelues caſt into priſon: the King in the meane time foreſeeing, that they wil not be able to pay the debt, being moued with pitty, he maketh a new edict, that if any of the debters wil deſire to be releaſed, before the day of paiment, hee will freely forgiue them. You ſee, <hi>B.</hi> the bill is iuſt and ſure. for he requires nothing but his owne: you ſee alſo that the Edict is good and firme; for by it hee ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours the poore miſerable ſoules that otherwiſe ſhould periſh in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: you ſee the Bill is contrary to the Edict; for that adiudgeth the not paier to perpetuall bondage: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, the Edict frees him that paieth not, ſo he pray to bee pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: further, you ſee, the Bond e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by the edict; for all that will reioice for the benefit thereof, doe no leſſe ſatisfie the King, then if they had fully paid all the debt due by the Bill: for the King requires his fummes, either by the vſurers ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerity,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:27055:42"/>or by his great equity ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards thoſe that craue releaſe: the firſt, by law; the latter by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour; if thou doſt either, thou doeſt ſufficient. Laſtly, <hi>B.</hi> you ſee what you would not: namely, that the Bill doth not command any asking of pardon, no it admits no ſuch matter, it cals either for paiment or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nothing elſe: for the free be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of asking pardon pertaines on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to the Edict. Goe to then, let the Decalogue be the Bill, let the law of promiſe be the Edict or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of free pardon; namely, <hi>the grace of the Meſſias:</hi> let faith be the asking of pardon: I will not mince it ſmaller, a word is enough to a wiſe man. Behold, now <hi>B.</hi> the fruit of your outcrying, the ſeeds whereof this twenty yeeres you haue diſperſed, with ſuch roughneſſe of words and impotency of minde, that you ought to beare it more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, if the truth now take ſome puniſhment of you: For beleeue me <hi>B.</hi> euery error ſhall ſuffer puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:27055:42"/>ſhall ſuffer, I ſay, at the hands of truth, either ſooner or later; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there a more certaine houre of ſinning, then of ſuffering. Call to minde with me that day, wherein applauding your ſelfe in your ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, you challenged one in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities; to whom, when as it was not lawfull to anſwere or reply ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently vnto you, making the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, either for the authority of your part, or for the obſcurity of your Sophiſtrie, and ſnares of your ſubtilties; good God, how you cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed ouer him. Neither did you thinke it ſufficient onely, this your poore lecture, to bee publiſhed in triumph of this ſo baſe victory, that it might bring darkeneſſe to the light, except alſo the ſixt yeere after (dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing in the funerals of the truth) you cauſed to bee publiſhed a new Commentary of the excellency and dignity of the law, an eternall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of your ignorance &amp; blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for it is almoſt incredible, how in that worke you mingle hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:27055:43"/>and earth together, and make ſquared things ſtraight: how often in that little booke, you put <hi>foedus</hi> for <hi>foedere:</hi> The law for the law; faith for faith, <hi>viz.</hi> a lie for a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie: and that which is a ſigne of a minde ſmally ingenious, how oft doe you make monſters to your ſelfe, which you might eaſily make away? I accuſe you not, the matter it ſelfe ſpeaketh; you ſhall be iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of your owne papers. This one thing I would haue you vnderſtand (whereof <hi>B.</hi> you ſhall be an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to poſterity, while this worke ſhall liue, and it ſhall liue foreuer:) That the booke of God is a booke indeed full of eies within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and written on both ſides, but withall ſealed; ſo that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hard things in it, which you <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowiſts</hi> doe not vnderſtand. But if you deſire to open your cloſets to enter into the inwards of it, you had need of a key: I meane not that which <hi>Rome</hi> reioiceth in, which openeth the bottomleſſe pit, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:27055:43"/>bringeth out monſtrous lies, and blaſphemies: neither doe I meane that key, <hi>B.</hi> which laieth vp for thee a great heape of ſiluer, which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth great increaſe to the dropſie of thy couetouſneſſe: neither doe I meane that key which openeth the ſmokes of Sophiſtry, and the meere froth of words, and of Diuine <hi>Plato</hi> and the Sophiſters, or ſuch like buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of darkeneſſe, and made wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But I meane <hi>B.</hi> the key of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that ſearcheth out the moſt ſecret things of the truth, and the hidden things of Gods wiſdome, and ſo openeth them that none can ſhut, and ſo ſhutteth them that none can open. Which key by your wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I am ſure you are without, as any thing that you want. And thus much of faith, the holineſſe whereof you haue defiled. Thus much alſo of the law, the maieſtie whereof you haue violared. And if any thing ſeeme leſſe ſpoken then ought to be, either for your deſerts, or as ſo weighty a matter requireth; let
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:27055:44"/>him thinke it is reſerued vntill ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other time, when God bleſſing our enterpriſes, wee ſhal haue more ſtrict examination of you vpon that booke, which you haue ſcribled of the excellency and dignity of the law. Jn the meane time, I bid you in Chriſt Ieſus to repent, and Farewell.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27055:44"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
